(Translated to English from Finnish Rally English)
(video link: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JnJ5bUT6s8Q)
Hello
Welcome. In this video I'll give you some tips
about how you could create the soundtrack
for your very first demoscene intro
using the SoundBox software synthesizer tracker
That is quite a specific topic
so I suppose you've had a very good reason to find it
and be watching now ...
My name is Paavo Nieminen
Here you see some nicknames or 'handles'
("qma" & "The Old Dude")
that I've used over the years
when producing my own productions to
demoscene intro competitions. They are
nothing spectacular. You can easily make
a much nicer demo or intro than I have ever done.
In addition, I have also given workshops
about how people can do their first demos.
In this video, I try to gather some of the learnings
that I think will make it smoother for you
to make your first intro.
One of the things is to create a soundtrack
perhaps even before going to a workshop or hackathon
so you can focus on the programming and creative part
when you have already made your soundtrack.
We have made some choices here:
We are looking at "intro" competitions
which means very small demos,
something like 4 kilobytes maximum file size
in the competition.
We are using JavaScript programming language
on the Web Browser platform
because in that specific scenario
SoundBox provides a quite good balance
between different constraints.
Ok - So, we are doing a soundtrack smoothly
for your first demoscene intro of 4 kilobytes
in JavaScript, using the SoundBox tracker.
Let's get down to business...
Let's have a desktop share
and a small speaker corner in the upper right...
I have 6 points to cover.
I'll start with the most important one
which I think is this...
This might seem obvious
but unfortunately people make mistakes with this -
I don't want you to make this mistake
so I emphasize this here:
Be safe with copyrights -
don't use any melodies
or other stuff from songs of others!
You might feel tempted to use something
from a hit song or a TV show
It could seem like a nice idea for your intro
but don't do that - it is definitely forbidden
in competition rules of demoscene events.
Intros are streamed and archived
so they become copies of work
and you want to really respect the copyrights of others
and do only your own, new, stuff here.
I promise that it is going to be much fun
building your own melody that is not a copy
or replication of anything from anybody else
Keep this in mind, and we'll be safe.
The next point is also important:
Don't take it too seriously -
we're here to have fun
and not to make the perfect production
on the first time ever
You don't have to be the next Mozart
you don't have to win the Eurovision song contest
It is quite possible that you're not even going
to win this first intro competition
Accepting this fact
enables us to have so much fun
in being creative and doing our own song
for the soundtrack and not judge ourselves
for its aesthetical values and "greatness"
You can be really proud
to just make new cool-sounding stuff
and completing this first intro
and making it into the competition that you have in mind.
I hope this encourages you to
push through to the end
and accept your own production
even if it is not perfect
and you can still be so proud that you have made it!
With these two things in mind
it is safe to move on
towards composing using SoundBox.
Before we open SoundBox, I'll prepare you
with the first point about it:
I think it is important that you
take some time and energy in the beginning
to really understand and learn what the 'tracker' structure
of a song is and how you edit that in SoundBox.
We'll see that in a minute
but I want you to focus first on this point
and the important word "understand" in there
in addition to just jumping in and having fun
I emphasize this because
in earlier workshops it has become a problem
later in the production
when changes to the song are needed
but it could have become a bit messy
because there has not been understanding
of what the song elements and parts
seen in the user interface actually mean.
Let's now open SoundBox ...
[Whispering, to let others sleep in the house:]
This is what SoundBox looks like
when you first open it.
You open it by just going to the website
https://sb.bitsnbites.eu/
Then it opens in your browser
and works in your browser.
So, it is very easy to just start using SoundBox
SoundBox greets you with a welcome text
that prompts you to open a demo song to get started
At some point, you should do that
and explore how the demo songs are made. But here
I want to emphasize the very important link
on the welcome message: "Help"
You really should click on "Help"
SoundBox has a very good help page
that has all the details
that I'm trying not to cover in this video.
My important message here is
that you should remember to read the help
and keep it by your side while you are learning
to use SoundBox.
The example songs can be opened
using the "Open" button on the left
You can explore how they have been made.
For this video, though, I'll click on "New"
so we start with a completely blank song.
We can just click on the virtual keyboard
on the lower right corner of the user interface
and see - actually we hear - sounds [synth beeps]
You can hear the sounds when you click
and you can see notes appearing one after each other
in what the help calls the "pattern editor"
(I said "pattern view" on the video, mistakenly)
I'll show you in practice
a couple of things from the help
No details, but ideas
So, these notes that you enter form a 'pattern'
Each pattern is always numbered and
the pattern number appears on the left, inside the 'song'.
Now we have one pattern here, numbered 0
and it contains those notes that were clicked just before.
You can always listen to the current song
by clicking the "Play" button.
It will generate a full song audio file
and start looping it over and over
And here we already have our first song
made with SoundBox - how cool is that!
Completely original... hehe...
We can do better after getting used to editing...
Quite soon you will want to start using
the computer keyboard for editing
I will now add a keyboard camera here
so you will see what I'm doing
Now my physical computer keyboard
is laid on top of that virtual synth keyboard on video
You want to start using the keyboard to enter notes soon
(is my suggestion, because it makes it easier for you...)
The computer keys match the musical keyboard notes
You have the notes of a musical keyboard
in your computer keyboard
You have 2 octaves:
lower one starting from 'Z'-key (matching a C-note)
higher one starting from 'Q'-key (C-note +1 octave)
By pressing these keys the pattern is updated
and you can always preview the song by clicking "Play"...
[musical notes playing]
And WOW ...
even by pressing random white keys
you have created a musical atmosphere
that remains interesting for at least a while
and could be suitable for an intro maybe
Okay. We can do better - moving on ...
You can make new notes from the keyboard,
move around with the arrow keys (as shown)
and delete notes using the 'Delete'-key
You probably don't want a note in every time slot...
So far you must have observed
that time goes from top to bottom
The tempo (how fast time goes) can be changed
by entering a number in the BPM field (beats per minute)
So - this is how you edit a pattern.
Then
you make a song by repeating a sequence of patterns.
So far we have 'pattern 0'.
You can switch focus
between pattern editor and song editor by clicking.
In the song editor, you can go to an empty space
and insert a number of a pattern
You can move with the arrow keys
and lay out the numbered patterns that you make
You may have guessed...
In addition to number 0, you can have 1, 2, 3, etc.
When you insert a number that has not been used
you get a blank pattern
that you can start filling in.
Sometimes we want to copy and paste a pattern
and then modify it a little bit
From the song, you can pick a pattern to be copied.
You don't use "customary" key shortcuts to copy...
Instead, click the copy button below the pattern editor
Let's click on copy here...
this is not very easy to find
if you don't know it, or learn from the help page
First you need to select the area to be copied
then you can click on copy,
move to location where to paste
and click paste.
[silence while examining a possible misclick]
Yeah, maybe I misclicked...
Now I have made a copy of pattern 0 to pattern 1
Then I can modify pattern 1
For example by selecting all the notes
and making them go down a couple of semitones
This kind of simple tools are available to
copy, paste, and transpose (-1,+1,-12,+12) selected notes
If you want to modify more, you can enter new notes
from the keyboard.
So far it has been pretty random notes and
now I have a song consisting of 2 different patterns
numbered 0 and 1.
Let's play the song...
[random notes playing]
Well - it's not genious ...
but it sound interesting and could be useful
and this is basically how you make a song
(also with less randomness...)
Now you just need to add more instruments, perhaps
For that purpose, you need to understand
how instruments work in SoundBox.
They are called 'tracks'
and they are found as the columns of the song editor
The columns go down from the top
with pattern numbers on top of each other
Each of these columns is a different track
that can have an instrument different from the others.
You have those 16 tracks that you can see
so you can have 16 different instruments
In a small 4-kilobyte intro you will have to limit
a little bit - we'll talk about that later.
But you can have at least a few different instruments.
Here is a very important thing to understand:
The 0 and 1 (and 2, 3, ...) in the first column
are different from 0 and 1 (or 2, 3, ...) in any other track
Remember to start pattern numbers from 0 on all tracks
This is important because of the file size
that will matter with intros - we'll get back to that later
For now, it is important to understand the structure:
Columns of the left "matrix" or table are instruments
They can be different from each other.
Each instrument has a different set of patterns
Here in the example,
we now have made 'pattern 0' for the second instrument (track)
and we can enter notes in the pattern editor
Let's insert some notes and preview the song
Okay,
now we have two different tracks, okay...
Then you want to have instruments that sound different
You do this with the synthesizer editor on the right.
You can play with the preset sounds
from the preset drop-down menu at the top
Then you can experiment how the sound changes
when you fiddle with the sound parameter sliders
If you have experience with synthesizers
you'll find a familiar two-oscillator additive synthesis
with a simple envelope
You don't have any way to sustain and release a note at will
SoundBox synth has only attack, constant sustain time, and release
You don't easily change the length of a note
Now I've selected a preset called "Base drum 1"
to the second instrument (track)
The sound is like a bass drum
We can now make a beat in 'pattern 0' of the second track
which has a bass drum -like instrument now
Let's repeat pattern 0
Patterns 1 and 2 and so on work the same way
and they are different from the same numbers in other song columns
In intros, use small, consecutive numbers
It will help you a lot
Let's preview the song...
[random notes with bass drum at 120 beats per minute]
If you change any parameters of the sound
the name will stop being the preset name
you can always go back to some preset sound
to start experimenting
Your own sounds don't have a name
Okay - that's how you structure a song.
One more thing about the instrument editor
You have the third editor view with a column
that can record changes to an instrument
For your first intro this can be a little confusing
because of reasons explained more in the help page
You might achieve great effects with it
but also confusion at some point.
So, maybe you could experiment with the third column editor later
and stick to instruments that remain the same throughout the song
So each track on the left has one instrument
and you can keep it simple by not changing them on the fly
Then you just create patterns
and repeat them in the song.
Then...
with this kind of understanding
I can safely let you do experimentation by yourself
and looking at the example songs
because then you can find this kind of structure in them
and can better understand those examples of what can be done
Of course, most importantly,
you can just start doing your own songs
pretty easily
like so...
using your keyboard
Observe: with the Tab-key you can switch between editors
Tab goes to right, shift+tab to left
and then you have the arrow keys
and then it's all under control using your keyboard.
What else about the user interface ...
things that may have caused confusion?
[silence while thinking hard]
Nothing comes to my mind right away..
Some things to observe though...
[sound quality issues with random notes and bass drum beat]
[because of drawing red highlight on volume indicators]
I was going to say:
Observe the volume meters on top of the song editor
You don't want to go far on the red zone
because then you get out of control
with your distortion. What you can do is
you can manage the 'drive' level of your instruments
which makes them louder or softer
So you can balance your instruments
and see that the total volume doesn't go to the red zone
very much because then it gets out of control.
If you want actual "distortion" (as a wanted effect)
you should use the distortion effect (slider called 'Dist') of the instrument
but 'Drive' it less to keep the total volumes below red
That is one thing to remember while getting creative with sounds
About the user interface...
The keyboard can enter notes as shown
You have to have a pattern to enter notes
Let's put 'pattern 0' of third instrument
and pick any sound
I was going to show you
how you can use the '' keys to change octave
The same symbols appear in the clickable octave change buttons
on each side of the virtual keyboard
It is quite simple to change octaves
lower and higher as shown and heard here
[Synth sounds from multiple octaves; keyboard tapping]
Octave down with '<'
Octave up with '>'
Then I let you experiment ...
Some limitations:
Even though you could make Waltz kind of music
with 3 beats per bar or some other number of beats per bar
counting to 3, 5, 7 or whatever in your music
you could do that (using the 'RPP' / 'rows per pattern' selector)
but SoundBox behaves much nicer with the default 4 beats per bar
[tonal information happening]
So... whoah... we're in musical spheres already!
Totally random...
but let's just have fun ...
I'm super proud of this production!
With these points in mind and
especially this understanding of the song structure
I'm sure that given some time you will
actually have control over your song
and the end result doesn't have to be
the randomness that I'm creating here when
showing you things on-the-fly in half an hour
I hope you get into control
using this understanding of the structure, learning it first.
I think it is time for a next point about intro soundtrack ...
The next point is:
Save often and keep track of versions
[sounds of learning to use streaming software]
Point number 4: Save often and keep track of versions...
Saving is very easy with SoundBox -
It's almost too easy and perhaps
a little bit of showing and explaining will help in the beginning
There is this "Save" button that you can click
and then it looks like this
It gives you a jumbled-looking URL to this same site
and indeed
the song data is in the end of the URL
which is very clever ...
You can just copy this address anywhere you like
My humble suggestion is to use a code text editor -
the one that you're going to use also for programming
Here, for example, is only the system text editor
not so suitable for coding
but just to show you the idea with a most simple tool
for saving the URL.
So there: you have your song saved now
as long as you remember to save this document
To keep the example complete, I'll save the file
and name it "versions_of_my_song.txt"
It is just text like any programming code would be text as well
Now that version is saved
At any time I can just go to my text editor
and copy the URL into the address bar of a browser
SoundBox will then open with the song data
The data of the song is now back to be edited
How nice...
Any change you make
for example add patterns 2, 3, 4 and some notes in pattern 4 ...
makes is a different version now.
Let us save again:
Just copy the URL from the "Save Song" dialog
and put it in a safe place in your editor
preferably a better editor than your system default
And then you can annotate
writing descriptions
like "this version of the song could be to long"
or whatever texts. You can manage your versions like this
It is very easy and simple
and you can finally include your song as a URL
as a comment in your intro source codes
That's nice. Now, the point was: save often
and somehow keep track of these versions
because otherwise you might accidentally do some damage
by just pressing delete too many times
or you can get lost in some ideas that end up being not good
But never mind - you can just come back to a version
that you have annotated and have the URL
Just copy the address,
put it in your browser
and you get back to your safe, good, annotated version
So, I think this is one very important thing to remember
to make your first intro soundtrack go smoothly.
You won't lose good versions because you remember to save often
and you have annotated the saved versions
It is so simple - remember to do it!
Towards the next point I think
The next point is:
Mind the file size -
this is important especially for intro competitions
in which you have the size limitation.
Let's go back to SoundBox
In an intro, you have a hard limitation, say 4 kilobytes,
for everything -
that includes the software synthesizer part of SoundBox
see its help page for details
Then, the song data - all the notes and patterns -
has to be there
And of course your graphics, your story - everything
has to be in the 4 kilobytes, which is very little
So, you really have to mind the file size.
In SoundBox, there is this check box 'Display file size'
I suggest you start using it
When checked, SoundBox will keep displaying two numbers
I'm not sure how visible the small font is on video
but you can experiment with it by yourself
while learning how to make songs
You can see two measurements:
The first number is the length of the song in JavaScript
when it is finally exported to be used in the intro program
by clicking on the 'JS/JavaScript' download button
You can view the downloaded JavaScript if you want to -
(never mind if programming is a new thing to you, no worries...)
the download is in JavaScript programming language
It begins with some comments with instructions
that explain about programming
but this video is not about the programming part ...
Still, (even without deeper programming),
you can see the structure that ends up inside your intro:
The notes and patterns become numbers
and all of them take up some space.
The first number that is shown with 'Display file size'
is the size of that code that we just saw
as JavaScript source code.
That is not the actual number of bytes consumed in your intro
because usually some tricks are applied using automatic tools
before your production is finalized
It will be compressed using something like a ZIP-compression.
Thus, the second number ('Compressed JS') is more important
In this example so far,
the compressed size of that songs's data
is now 302 bytes (if the font is visible...)
You can see these numbers all the time
while you compose and compare versions of your soundtrack
So, remember to click on 'Display file size'
and look at the numbers time to time.
I can't give you any maximums to aim for
It all depends on the compromise you eventually do
between your graphical and song elements
and the length of the whole show
and maybe there is some time
to innovate ways to reduce the code size
in certain places ...
So, I can't give you a rule about
which number of bytes you should aim for
But you must remember that here less is less, always -
so you have to be mindful of the size
if you really want to get your production done
for a 4 kilobyte intro competition.
You can observe how the numbers change:
for example, if you add
one more repetition of 'pattern 0' of the first track here
You find out that the JavaScript now contains more data
but the actual compressed size is still the same
because there are things happening in the compression
Also, eventually the thing is compressed
with all the other code
So these figures are not exact
but they give you some kind of clues
Let's add some more to the example ...
If you are very repetitive
the song might become boring
so don't repeat all the time, but
whatever you repeat will be compressed better
because of the compression algorithm
So, some tricks like repetition can be applied
and you should avoid some easy mistakes
like using accidentally letters as pattern numbers
Now when I put a 'pattern A' there
it immediately produces a larger size
than any number 0-9
Observe: the later alphabet you use the more bytes it needs
You can explore from the JavaScript how this actually works
But even without understanding programming
you can see the effect from these size numbers
It is not good to include any funny text messages
in the song data even for the fun of it ...
You will end up using too much space.
That is the reason why you should stick with small numbers
and not leave any gaps between the pattern numbers, finally
Yeah, and you can always explore how your choices
affect the size
Here, I put a big letter as a pattern number
which is stupid because it costs so many bytes
compared to putting a 0 (329 bytes vs. 320 bytes here)
Depending on also the locations - how many tracks you use -
you could be using more bytes
Putting a new 'pattern 0' here in the 5th instrument (track)
uses some bytes, okay, ...
but if I accidentally use a track that is more on the right (like 15)
the file size is bigger
because the knowledge of nothing happening between tracks
is stored.
What you want to do in a 4 kilobyte intro is
you want to have small numbers like 0, 1, ...
close to the left side of the song editor
That's what you aim for
and the tool that you use is 'Display file size'
Remember that the size is approximate
so in the longer run
you also need to test, compile your intro
and see what the actual final size would be
But while you are making the soundtrack
you can approximate
and see the effect of the choices that you make
Here was my point number 5
important for you to succeed
in making your first demoscene intro
as smoothly as possible.
I think I have one more point to go ...
The final point:
Be prepared to leave stuff out
What this means...
[sounds of learning to use a streaming software]
"To leave stuff out" means that eventually
you will probably end up having to do a compromise
between your original plan of what you wanted
to tell in your intro story
and how much graphics you can fit in
and how much music.
So, it is quite possible that you have to leave something out
for many reasons.
So, it is good to prepare for this -
mentally, which comes back to the earlier points
about not being to hard on yourself
and managing expectations on your first ever intro
But now, thinking about a smooth process
it will help if you keep this in mind from the onset:
When you create your song,
you can structure it so that
maybe there is a main melody
or those beats that you really, really want there to be
the "main thing" built in the leftmost tracks
Then you could have additional ones
that could be left out if need be
Also, you should somehow plan also the concept of your intro
so that you know what is the main thing
and that could help you leave out additional things
that "could have been nice"
Knowing what is the main thing will enable you
to survive with leaving the other things out
and to focus on the one thing that you get finished
You can do this preparation technically
in the structure of your song.
Maybe I'll try finding a longer song as an example
from some earlier production of my own
In my recent downloads there is one from years ago
an entry called "Tilestys"
Probably I have the song as a comment in the source code
so we could look at it as an example
Ok, I found it and opened it in the editor
Looks like it was in 2018 - time flies past
My annotations for song versions was not super good
but I suppose these are exactly
versions that I've made during the very last hours
of making that intro
and they are experiments on what could stay or be left out
If there was more time back then
the annotations could have been more accurate
Let's load one version and look at it after 6 years
Ok - here you can see my own attempt
Let's see if I could play it here on the video
[soundtrack of "Tilestys" playing; with unwanted crackling]
Yep, this computer could be too slow for streaming
But we can see how the song is structured:
there is a lot of repetition going on
one trick "from the book"
but also some alterations
so that it doesn't become too boring too soon
kind of attempts to do this
Then there's a clearly different section
so there are kind of different phases in the intro
not enough of course ...
it's not perfect ...
but then... my point 2 was "Let's have fun"
and be merciful about the quality of these productions
Anyway, if it should have happened
that I ran out of time to make the intro
and there was absolutely not enough graphics
to sustain interest for as much time as this song lasts
I could perhaps be happy about being prepared -
it looks like there is a separate part
that could be left out
so that a shorter running time could be made
more interesting by adding something there
and leaving out the rest.
It is as easy as loading this version and deleting those final parts
Another thing is the apparently infrequent 'pattern 0' on track 6
maybe a low base note (remembered wrong; it's a cymbal-like noisy sound)
It makes some interesting thing in the song
but if there was absolute need to add something to the graphics
maybe I could just delete it
and see how it would affect the size
It turns out that it could give me a lot of bytes for the graphics
Let's check if I had done that stupid mistake of empty tracks in between..
No.. there was stuff in all the tracks in the final song
The final point was:
prepare to leave stuff out
and now after 6 years I remember more about this track
If need be, track 6 (with occasional cymbal sound)
could be left out
Then you get 70 bytes
to make a nice fade-out or other polishing to graphics
It goes two ways:
if you really want to add something to the song
then you end up leaving stuff out from the graphics
or story, or running time or something
I think that is a hard thing about intros but also
the main interesting thing about the whole hobby
why else should we even have these competitions
with limitations of executable file size
It's fun and you can get hooked on finding the perfect compromise
which can never be found ultimately
So, that was my point 6 about leaving stuff out
I think I've covered all the points now.
Some aspects of SoundBox that you can find in the help
but you may want to observe:
You can select a range and preview range only
like so
[soundtrack of "tilestys" playing from middle; crackling due to low-end computer]
And then in the patterns
you can have at most 4 notes play at the same time
using the same instrument sound
This is one way to possibly conserve space
and make interesting musical things happening
I won't go to any detail about the synthesizer part
because that would be off topic
Then it is time to recap ...
So, that's about it ...
I tried to remember things that have happened in intro workshops
I think all of these main points have history
of having happened sometimes:
People have made nice demos but copied music from others
and then the intros have to be disqualified
which is the best that can happen
because you can't go forward with somebody else's music
So, you be safe with copyrights!
Use only your own material.
This one is important - it has happened
that people are shy about their productions
they think that the product isn't cool or shiny enough
to go forward in a competition
But I think it is a shame
because in my opinion they have been very creative
and nice works, both music and graphics
I hope you can prepare yourself
for letting go of "serious business" here
and have fun and accept the result that you can produce
for your first intro.
Oh, it has happened that people have
forgotten to learn and understand the tool they use for music
so watching over their shoulder ...
you see random clicking of buttons here and there
which also usually produces too big a file size
So, I hope my tips help, one of which was
to read the help page of SoundBox and understand the tool
I hope you remember to do that too
Yes, #4 has happened to myself many times:
I get so caught up with creating the music
that I end up with a complete side-track
but I have forgotten to save an earlier version
That is a shame because it would be so easy to save
the URL-format of a snapshot of your song
many times and keep track of the versions
so that you can find an earlier version
if you get lost
Try to be mindful of that.
The file size was covered -
you have many things you can do to manage it
Finally, you can prepare both technically and also mentally
for leaving stuff out
because everything comes with the cost of some more bytes
and the whole idea of the intro competition is the maximum size
and applying your creativity within that constraint.
It doesn't have be too painful -
a way to achieve this is to
create options from which you can pick, mix and match parts
and leave out those not essential to the main message
in your demo
This is also a good thing that enables you
to really focus on the key ideas
forcing you to be creative
I believe that it will make you better
in your next project in any field of life, study, or work:
You have practiced focusing on the essence
here, having fun in a demoscene intro competition
Okay...
I don't think I have anything more to say here
So, have a good time tracking
and see you at a demo party!
Thank you for watching. See you!